Guide to the Warren Jay Vinton papers, 1932-1969
Vinton, Warren Jay papers, 1932-1969
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Warren Jay Vinton papers, 1932-1969
2946
Warren Jay Vinton, 1889-1969.
28 cubic ft.
Correspondence, memoranda, telegrams, minutes, reports, pamphlets, programs, newsletters, membership lists, reprints, speeches, press releases, broadsides, clippings, photographs, and copies of legislative hearings and bills.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Consists primarily of correspondence, memoranda, telegrams, minutes, reports, pamphlets, programs, newsletters, membership lists, reprints, speeches, press releases, broadsides, clippings, photographs, and copies of legislative hearings and bills documenting Vinton's active role in designing and implementing federal housing policies from 1935 to 1957. Papers concern many aspects of governmental activity in the public housing area, including low-income housing, defense housing, housing for the elderly, racial policy in public housing, and particularly the development and passage of housing legislation and congressional investigations of federal housing practices. In addition to Vinton's own work, the papers document the work and opinions of many other planners, architects, housing experts, economists, federal administrators, and politicians.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Warren J. Vinton received his A.B. from the University of Michigan in 1911. At age 21 he became secretary and director of the Vinton Company, then the largest general building contractors in Detroit. During World War I he served as an assistant attaché at the U.S. Embassy in Paris. In 1928 he went to New York and worked for the American Association for Social Security, which did the groundwork for the eventual adoption of social security legislation. He also did graduate work in economics and statistics at Columbia University. In 1934 Vinton was appointed a field research supervisor with the newly formed Federal Housing Administration, where he developed the basic research techniques used in the first housing census done by the Census Bureau in 1940. When the Resettlement Administration was established in 1935, he was put in charge of economic and sociological studies for greenbelt towns and helped select the locations for three of them. From 1935-37 he assisted Senator Robert F. Wagner in drafting housing legislation which became the Wagner Act of 1937, and he later headed the social and economic studies which led to further public housing legislation adopted in 1949. He then became assistant commissioner of the new Public Housing Administration, where he remained until his retirement in 1957. He then became mayor of Somerset, Maryland, and retired in April, 1968.
Vinton belonged to, or was a board member of, the Washington Housing Association, the National Housing Conference, the American Society of Planning Officials, and the American Institute of Planners.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Consists primarily of correspondence, memoranda, telegrams, minutes, reports, pamphlets, programs, newsletters, membership lists, reprints, speeches, press releases, broadsides, clippings, photographs, and copies of legislative hearings and bills documenting Vinton's active role in designing and implementing federal housing policies from 1935 to 1957. Most are administrative records produced during his tenure as Chief of Research in the Suburban Resettlement Division of the Resettlement Administration (1935-1937), Chief Economist and Planning Officer of the U.S. Housing Authority (1937-1949), and First Assistant Commissioner of the Public Housing Administration (1949-1957). Also included are records of the Central Housing Committee (1935-1942), on which Vinton represented the Resettlement Administration and later the U.S. Housing Authority, and of the Advisory Committee of the Bureau of the Census for the 1940 Federal Census of Housing. Papers concern many aspects of governmental activity in the public housing area, including low-income housing, defense housing, housing for the elderly, racial policy in public housing, and particularly the development and passage of housing legislation and congressional investigations of federal housing practices.
In addition to Vinton's own work, the papers document the work and opinions of many other planners, architects, housing experts, economists, federal administrators, and politicians, including Charles Abrams, Tracy B. Auger, Edmund N. Bacon, Catherine Bauer, Russell Van Nest Black, John B. Blandford, Jr., Lawrence N. Bloomberg, Walter H. Blucher, Ernest J. Bohn, Harry F. Byrd, Henry S. Churchill, Jacob L. Crane, Frank R. Creedon, Frederick A. Delano, Henry Ellenbogen, Herbert Emmerich, Raymond M. Foley, Philip M. Glick, Sergei N. Grimm, Justin Hartzog, Benjamin H. Higgins, John Ihlder, Leon H. Keyserling, Philip M. Klutznick, David L. Krooth, J.S. Lansill, Albert Mayer, Bleecker Marquette, Joseph R. McCarthy, Lewis Mumford, Dillon S. Myer, Charles F. Palmer, Horace W. Peaslee, Elbert Peets, Hugh R. Pomeroy, Don K. Price, Franklin D. Roosevelt, James W. Routh, Boris B. Shiskin, Charles E. Slusser, Clarence S. Stein, Nathan Straus, Rexford G. Tugwell, Sir Raymond Unwin, Robert F. Wagner, Jesse R. Wolcott, Edith E. Wood, Elizabeth Wood, Coleman Woodbury, and Wilson W. Wyatt. Also included are documents related to the work of municipal housing authorities, including those of Syracuse and New York, N.Y., Winston-Salem, N.C., Chicago, Ill., Washington, D.C.; activities of professional organizations, including the National Association of Housing Officials, National Housing Conference, and the American Society of Planning Officials; and Vinton's consulting work.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Vinton, Warren Jay, 1889-1969.; Abrams, Charles, 1902-1970.; Augur, Tracy Baldwin, 1896-1974.; Bacon, Edmund N.; Bauer, Catherine, 1905-; Black, Russell Van Nest, 1893-1969.; Blandford, John, 1914-; Bloomberg, Lawrence N.; Blucher, Walter H. (Walter Harold), 1901-; Bohn, Ernest J.; Byrd, Harry Flood, 1887-1966.; Churchill, Henry S.; Crane, Jacob L. (Jacob Leslie), 1892-1988.; Creedon, Frank R.; Delano, Frederic Adrian, 1863-1953.; Ellenbogen, Henry.; Emmerick, Herbert.; Foley, Raymond M.; Glick, Philip M.; Grimm, Sergei N.; Hartzog, Justin R., 1892-1963.; Higgins, Benjamin Howard, b. 1912.; Ihlder, John, 1876-1958.; Keyserling, Leon Hirsch.; Klutznick, Philip M.; Krooth, David L.; Lansill, J. S.; Mayer, Albert.; Marquette, Bleecker.; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-; Myer, Dillon S.; Palmer, Charles F.; Peaslee, Horace W.; Peets, Elbert, 1886-1968.; Pomeroy, Hugh R. (Hugh Reynolds), 1899-1961.; Price, Don Krasher.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Routh, James W.; Shiskin, Boris B.; Slusser, Charles E.; Stein, Clarence S.; Straus, Nathan, 1889-1961.; Tugwell, Rexford G. (Rexford Guy), 1891-; Unwin, Raymond, Sir, 1863-1940.; Wagner, Robert F. (Robert Ferdinand), 1877-1953.; Wolcott, Jesse R.; Wood, Edith E.; Wood, Elizabeth.; Woodbury, Coleman.; Wyatt, Wilson W.; American Association for Social Security.; American Institute of Planners.; American Society of Planning Officials.; National Association of Housing Officials.; National Housing Conference.; United States. Bureau of the Census.; United States. Federal Housing Administration.; United States. Federal Public Housing Authority.; United States. Public Housing Administration.; United States. Resettlement Administration.; Vinton Company.; Washington Housing Association.
Subjects:
City planning.; Housing--Law and legislation.; Public housing--Law and legislation.; Social security.; Mayors--Maryland--Somerset.
Places:
Detroit (Mich.)
Form and Genre Terms:
Bills (legislative records).; Broadsides--United States--20th century.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Greenbelt Towns, Resettlement Administration.
Card File and Printed Matter, 1936-1957. File listed alphabetically by name; articles listed alphabetically by title.
Boxes 15 and 24
Series II. Chief Economist.
Office Files [1934-1945]-1949 (1935-1937 in Resettlement Administration; 1937-1942 in U. S. Housing Authority; 1942-1949 in National Housing Authority)-comprised of those files listed on his office file folder listing that survived [Listed alphabetically by folder title]
Boxes 1-5, 7-8, 13, 14, 17, 18-20, 22, 24 and 28
Series III. Chief Economist
Supplemental Office Files, 1945-1949-files not included in original listing. Listed alphabetically
Boxes 1-3, 7, 9, 10, 12-14 and 17-20
Series IV. First Assistant Commissioner, Public Housing Authority, file, 1949-1957
Listed Alphabetically
Boxes 1, 10, 16, 17, 19, 20 and 23
Series V. Consultant Files 1957-1966. Listed Alphabetically
Boxes 1, 4, 13, 15, 20, 21, 23 and 24
Series VI. Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports, Chronologically Arranged, 1935-1969
Boxes 18 and 20
Series VII. Subject Arrangement, 1941-1956
Boxes 1, 20, 23 and 27
Series VIII. Housing Legislation
Boxes 5, 6 and 27
Series IX. U.S. Housing Act Amendments
Boxes 6, 7, 21 and 27
Series X. Wanger, Ellender, Taft Bill, 1945-1946
Boxes 7, 8 and 27
Series XI. Wanger, Ellender-Taft Housing Act, 1947-1948
Boxes 9, 10, 22 and 27
Series XII. U.S. Congress Joint Committee on Housing, 1947-1948
Box 11
Series XIII. Housing Acts
Boxes 10, 11, 21, 22, 26 and 27
Series XIV. Warren Jay Vinton Speeches and Publications, 1936-1964, arranged by year
Box 16
Series XV. Articles, 1936-1964
Boxes 16, 17 and 23
Series XVI. Organizations and Conferences, 1949-1969
Boxes 15, 18, 25 and 26
Series XVII. Newspaper Clippings, 1935-1966
Box 23
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Greenbelt Towns, Resettlement Administration. Card File and Printed Matter, 1936-1937
  - Alphabetical card file on planners and architects and their qualifcations, prepared by Vinton in the fall of 1935 on request of Rexford Tugwell for selection for employment on Suburban Resettlement Greenbelt Town projects. (Box 15)
  - "Comparative Architectural Details in Greenbelt Housing," American Architect and Architecture (2 copies), Oct. 1936 (Box 24)
  - "Planned Community Appraised," Greenbelt, Md., The Architectural Forum, Jan. 1940 (Box 24)
  - An article by Henry Churchill entitled "American's Town Planning Begins," Reprint from New Republic, June 12, 1936 (Box 24)
  - O. Kline Fulmer's article entitled Greenbelt, Washington, American Council on Public Affairs, ca. 1941 (Box 24)
  - "The Meaning of the Greenbelt Towns," The New Republic, Feb. 12, 1937 (Box 24)
  - Maps, survey, photographs, pamphlets, brochures, First Annual Report of Resettlement Administration, 1936 (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: First Annual Report 1936; Interim Report, April 1936 (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: Greenhills, Ohio brochure (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: Greenbelt [Md.] brochure (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: Greendale, Wisconsin brochure (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: General Map of Greenhills Site (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: Map, General Land use for Greenbelt, Maryland (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: Boundary Survey, Greenbelt Area, Prince George County, Maryland (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Adminstration: Greenbelt Towns, Washington (2 copies). Lists staff of Suburban Resettlement pamphlet, September 1936 (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: America's Land, Washington, 1 volume (a pamphlet), 1936 (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: Pictures of Greenbelt with departmental stamp (6 pictures) (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: Pictures of Slums with departmental stamp (13 pictures) (Box 24)
  - Resettlement Administration: Resettlement Administration, Washington, pamphlet, 1936 (Box 24)
  - An article by Rexford G. Tugwell entitled "Magical Greenbelt is Rising Model Maryland Community," from Work, October 1938 (Box 24)
  - "Farm Security Administration Announces Greenbelt Rentals," U.S. Department of Agriculture. M.C. news release (2 copies), Sept. 2, 1937 (Box 24)
  - "Greenbelt Communities 1/25/40," U.S. Department of Agriculture, Farm Security Administration, M.C. news release (Box 24)
  - An article by Warren J. Vinton entitled "Greenbelt for Tomorrow (Ebenezer Howard) TS, ca. 1950 (Box 24)
  - You Can't Resettle Me! Saturday Evening Post, October 10, 1936 (Box 24)
- Series II. Chief Economist. Office Files [1935-1945]-1949
  - "A-Miscellaneous" Correspondence, 1938-1947 (Box 1)
  - "Abrams, Charles"-Correspondence, articles, 1938-1945 (Box 1)
  - "Adequacy of Housing, Committee on" Reports of meetings, 1945 (Box 1)
  - "Advisory Groups" correspondence and lists of possible members for U.S. Housing Authority, 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Allotment of Funds, Application" Application for funds for post World War II low-rent housing, 1940-1943 (Box 1)
  - "Alternate Public Housing Scheme"-Rehabilitation Plan of Arthur Binns, Philadelphia, Penn., 1939-1940 (Box 28)
  - "Alternate Public Housing Schemes"-General Report: Report by Vinton on alternate schemes for public housing, 1939 (Box 28)
  - "Alternate Public Housing Scheme"-Lambert Plan: Lambert Housing Project at Princeton, N.J., 1938-1939 (Box 28)
  - "Alternate Public Housing Schemes"-Other Plans: Borsodi projects, Rutgerstown and Queenstown, N.Y.C., Mayer plan of self-endowed communitites, etc., 1939 (Box 28)
  - "Alternate Public Housing Scheme"-Public Service Building Corporation, N[ational] A[ssociation] of R[eal] E[state] B[oards]: recommendation for creation of Public Service Building Corporation, 1939 (Box 28)
  - "Alternate Public Housing Scheme"-USHA-FHA Cooperation (NAREB): cooperation in acquiring land and financing recommended by NAREB, 1939 (Box 28)
  - "Alternate Public Housing Schemes"-Wolcott Plan: federal insurance of local low-rent housing bond issues urged by Senator Wolcott (R), 1939 (Box 28)
  - "American Federation of Labor" Memoranda, recommendations, broadsides, 1936-1946 (Box 1)
  - "American Society of Planning Officials" correspondence, 1949 (Box 1)
  - "B-miscellaneous-correspondence, 1942-1946 (Box 1)
  - Bauer, Catherine, see Wurster, Catherine Bauer (Box 1)
  - "Book Reviews and Notices" TS reviews, 1937-1949 (Box 1)
  - "Census of Housing" correspondence, memoranda, testimony esp., 1939-1949 (Box 1)
  - "Census of Housing" Promotion and Legislation Census: requests, resolutions from Central Housing Committee, NANO, NAREB, etc. asking for inclusion of housing date in 1940 census, drafts of bill to provide for national census of housing, exerpts from Congressional Record, memoranda, correspondence, copies of 4 bills as introduced in Senate and House of Representatives reports resolutions for repeal amendment, etc. clippings, testimony in hearings, appropriation bills, etc., Jan. 20, 1936-Feb. 20, 1940 (Box 1)
  - "Central Housing Committee" 1935-1942
    - CHC Minutes 1935-1937: Minutes of organization meeting, September 27, 1935 (Box 1)
    - Confidential report of Special Committee for CHC consideration, report of Organization Committee, November 12, 1935 (Box 1)
    - Extract from 25th meeting of the Central Housing Committee, March 2, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of 30th meeting, January 12, 1939, excerpts from Minutes, file annotated "Materials taken by Mr. Straus to CHC meeting of Jan. 12, 1939.. .File with meeting of CHC 1/12/39" (Box 1)
    - CHC Reports: Present Activities and Organization of Federal Housing Agencies and Organization of Federal Housing Agencies #12, Confidential, Jan. 1936 (Box 1)
    - Activities and Organization of Federal Agencies Concerned with Housing, 1936 (Box 1)
    - Confidential report of the President including special section on housing policies and procedure and general section on Committee Organization and Operations, Jan. 30-31 1936 (Box 1)
    - 1st annual report, Sept. 30, 1936 (Box 1)
    - Report by F.A. Delano, "A Federal Housing Program Related to the Needs of the Lower Income Group", Jan. 4, 1937 (Box 1)
    - "General Summary covering Organization and Operations Program, Production and Personnel", June 8, 1937 (Box 1)
    - "Summary of Organization and Operations.. .Groups, Sections", June 30, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Report of Committe on Defense Housing, June 14, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Outline of Final Reports of.. .Committees and Subcommittes, April 20, 1942 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Economics and Statistics Final Report, March 8, 1942 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Coordination: Confidential report of Committee on Coordination of Housing Activities, May 24, 1935 (Box 1)
    - Copies of letters of transmittance by Frederick Delano, report of conference of the Committee on Coordination of Housing Activities of federal government, July 11, 1935 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence to Resettlement Administration and U.S. Housing Authority, agencies whom Vinton represented on Committee, concerning statements, policy, meetings, etc., letters announcing resignation and appointment chairmen; memoranda appoining W.J.V. as official representative, Oct. 31, 1935-Jan. 30, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Federal Housing Functions: Report, drafts, notes and memoranda on report of Sub-Committee on Federal Housing Functions (est. Jan. 29, 1936) considering housing program for low income groups and demarcation between public and private housing; report in two sections because of basic disagreement among Committee members, MC, TS and MS., Jan. 10-March 6, 1936 (Box 4)
    - Governors' meeting: Program of luncheon given by C.H.C. in honor of governors attending the inauguration and list of members CHC luncheon speech by Frederic Delano, chairman CHC on "Nation-wide Housing Policy", Jan. 19, 1936 (Box 1)
    - Minimum Cost House, Department of Commerce: Report of Subcommittee on Design and Construction on Minimum Price House, May 23, 1936 (Box 4)
    - Address by C.F. Palmer, Housing Coordinator of National Defense Advisory Commission to CHC, October 5, 1940 invitation to party on dispersal CHC July 24, 1942, statement by F.A. Delano on aims and organization of CHC (Box 1)
    - Planning and Initiation: Memorandum from Resettlement Administration; report on material available on housing needs; outline of studies within scope of Subcommittee on Planning and Intiation; planning criteria of Resettlement Administration Housing Division P.W.A., Federal housing Administration incl. Circular 3 on Low-Cost Housing proposal for study on housing, Feb.-March 1936 (Box 1)
    - Planning and Initiation-Glossary Section: Minutes of Sub-Committee on planning and initiation, Central Housing Committee; annotated glossary of housing terms; letter, Jan. 30 1936-Jan. 17, 1938 (Box 3)
    - Procedure and Administration-Love's Labor Lost: Chart on selected housing conditions, correspondence and drafts, outlines, report and revisions of "A Summary of Important Facts on Housing" prepared Feb. 1937 by Sub-committee on procedure and Administration for state governments and issued by National Emergency Council, Jan. 10, 1936-March 10, 1937 (Box 4)
    - Procedure and Administration-Policy C.H.C.: General questionnaire on housing policy from Sub-committee on Procedure and Administration of Central Housing Committee, drafts of responses and transcript of meetings of Resettlement Administration to formulate department's reply; Sub-committee report; revised versions of Sub-committee report incorporating and consolidating views on federal housing policy, Dec. 2, 1935-Jan. 29, 1936 (Box 3)
    - Research and Sat.-Foreign Housing Section: The British Government in Housing 1851-1935. A Housing Division PWA Study by Arthur Bessin; issued by the Foreign Housing Section, Central Housing Committee, Sub-committee on research and statistics, 1937 revised edition (Box 1)
  - "Central Statistical Board"-Fifth annual report 1938/39 memoranda on returns and services, July 1, 1938-July 24, 1939 (Box 19)
  - "Chicago, Ill."-correspondence, 1945 (Box 1)
  - "Chief Economist and Planning Officer"-memorandum on "Planning and Policy-Making in the United States Authority" submitted to Nathan Straus, Administrator for discussion, Aug. 19, 1939 (Box 1)
  - "Citizen's Housing Council of New York"-correspondence and report, 1945 (Box 1)
  - "Commissioner" correspondence, memoranda to commissioner, National Housing Agency, 1942-1944 (Box 1)
  - "Conference on Housing (Secretary Ickes)"-binder of "Material prepared for discussion of agenda," conference on housing policy held by secretary Ickes, Sept. 20, 1937 (Box 19)
  - "Coordination of Defense Housing"-executive order 8632 for Coordination of National Defense Housing and regulations governing defense housing coordination, Jan. 11, 1941 (Box 28)
  - "Cost Limitations"-statutory cost limitations on public housing projects, 1942 (Box 13)
  - "Costs and Estimates-Memoranda, charts, statements concerning construction costs, overall costs, comparisions, progress reports, answers to queries, March 29, 1938-Sept. 1947 (Box 28)
  - "Court Decisions on Public Housing"-two cases in Supreme Court of the United States, 1944 (Box 13)
  - "Defense Housing"-memoranda, correspondence and reports on U.S.H.A. participation in defense housing program from Nathan Straus, U.S.H.A. administrator, Leon Keyserling Deputy Administrator and C.F. Palmer, Defense Housing Coordinator, June 6, 1940-June 14, 1941 (Box 28)
  - "Defense Housing"-binder, indexed under drafts of bills, U.S.H.A. statements, CHC statements, Defense Council, N.A.H.O., miscellaneous statements, on participation of U.S.H.A. in defense housing projects, June 1940 (Box 28)
  - "Defense Housing-Memoranda and speeches on estimates of housing needs and cost for defense program, need for rental housing, defense workers' incomes etc., correspondence with National Committee on the Housing Emergency, comments on speeches by C.F. Palmer National Defense Housing Co-ordinator charts on distribution of public housing by various federal agencies, mainly between Vinton and Nathan Straus, administrator, Sept. 18-Jan. 26, 1942 (Box 28)
  - "Defense Housing"-Landam Act Legislative Hist. DH: Bill on Landa Act, H.R. 10412, Public No. 849 "To expedite the provision of housing in connection with national defense" indexed, numbered 1-19, Sept. 5-Oct. 14, 1940 (Box 28)
  - "Defense Housing"-Public #781 Legislative Hist. DH"-Congressional Record, House and Senate; Senate ammendments and report on additional authorization for defense housing, emergency supplemental estimate for defense housing, memoranda from Nathan Straus, U.S.H.A. to John Carody, F.W.A. on U.S.H.A. participation, Sept. 6, 1940-Dec. 10, 1941 (Box 28)
  - "Defense Housing Coordinator"-Press release on role of Defense Housing Coordinator, executive order and regulations, staff list, statement of racial policy, correspondence with C.F Palmer, Defense Housing Coordinator, Jacob Crane, Assistant Coordinator, annual report and report on crisis localities, Aug. 19, 1940-Dec. 4, 1941 (Box 28)
  - "Defense Housing Coordinator"-Memoranda and correspondence between C.F. Palmer, Defense Housing Coordinator and Nathan Straus, Vinton and others, U.S.H.A.on coordinating functions, relationships, and programs of housing agencies working on defense housing, July 20-Dec. 17, 1940 (Box 28)
  - "Rental Policy"-[Defense Housing Rental Policy] Statements of policy on defense housing rentals for army, navy industrial workers, and army civilian personnel, May 2-Oct. 15, 1941 (Box 7)
  - "Delano, Frederick A."-Memorandum and 5 drafts of report of Central Housing Committee on "A Federal Housing Program Related to the Needs of the Lower Income Groups," offspring of report as appeared in American City, Jan. 1937, correspondence on statement on report by J.S. Lansill, Resettlement Administrator, Setp. 16, 1936-Feb. 13, 1937, Sept. 14, 1944 (Box 28)